<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly sermon preached before the right worshipfull Edvvard Cooke Esquier Atturney Generall vnto the Queens most excellent Maiestie, and others of worship, in Tittleshall in Norfolke: by F.B.</title>
            <author>Bradley, Francis, fl. 1600.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16598</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3505</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116905</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852120</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852120</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17427</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16598)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17427)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1128:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly sermon preached before the right worshipfull Edvvard Cooke Esquier Atturney Generall vnto the Queens most excellent Maiestie, and others of worship, in Tittleshall in Norfolke: by F.B.</title>
                  <author>Bradley, Francis, fl. 1600.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Felix Kingston, for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Francis Bradley.</note>
                  <note>A sermon on 2nd Chronicles XXXIV, 17-18.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page torn.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17427:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17427:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A GODLY SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON PREACHED BEFORE THE RIGHT Worſhipfull EDVVARD COOKE <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier, Atturney Generall vnto the Queens most excellent Maiestie, and others of</hi> Worſhip, in Tittleſhall in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke: by <hi>F. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Babes, it is the laſt time, and as ye haue heard that Antichriſt ſhall come, euen now are there many Antichriſts, wherby we know that it is the laſt time.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Ioh. 1. Chap. 2. Verſ. 18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Babes, keepe your ſelues from Idols.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Ioh. 1. Chap. 5. Verſ. 21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Felix Kingston,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Man.</hi> 1600.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17427:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17427:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipfull <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Cooke</hi> Eſquier, Atturney Generall <hi>to the Queens most excellent Maieſtie,</hi> grace, mercie, and peace from God the Father, and from our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the ſinnes in generall (Right Worſhipfull) poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our peruerſenature, ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude chalengeth to hir ſelfe a ſpeciall propertie in vs, a thing repugnant to reaſon, diſagreeing to humanitie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the expectation of man: that it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeth with humanitie, Nature her ſelfe may beſt be Iudge, who hath not dealt ſo ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in bestowing of her gifts, but ſhe will cenſure him as moſt vnkind whom ſhee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth tardie in this ſin of ingratitude. Which ſinne (as it is common) ſo it is contagious, and hath infected many, and yet for my own part I deſire to be aſmuch as may be free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it; which I ſhould hardly be, if I ſhould bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſo many fauours receiued from your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb facs="tcp:17427:3"/>in the graue of forgetfulneſſe: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (in token of my dutie) I haue preſumed to publiſh this my poore talent vnder your good acceptance, deſiring your fauourable pardon for the ſame. I muſt confeſſe I ſtoode long in ſuſpence with my ſelfe vnto whom I ſhould commit this ſmall trauell; but your wonted affection, and zeale towards the word ſoone ſtirred me vp to preſent it vnto you, not being much diſmaied hauing ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons to induce me thereunto: among the reſt, this being one of the chiefeſt, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, your patient and godly attention when it was preached; of whom I may ſay as Paul ſaith to the Theſſalonians, you receiued it not as it was the word of man, but as it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede the word of God.
<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. chap. 2. verſ. 13.</note> Thus with my hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie prayer vnto Almightie God, that it will pleaſe his Maiestie to bleſſe you with many proſperous yeares and daies in this life, and in the end eternall life with eternall ioyes, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your worſhips moſt bounden to commaund</hi> Francis Bradley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:17427:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. CHRON. 24. CHAP. 17.18. VERSES.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And after the death of Ichoiada came the Princes of Iudah, and did reuerence to the King, and the King harkened vnto them:</p>
                  <p>And they left the houſe of the Lord God of their fathers, and ſerued groues and Idols, and wrath came vpon Iudah and Ieruſalem, becauſe of this their treſpaſſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this portion of Scripture (Right worſhipfull and beloued in our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt) the ſpirit of God ſetteth downe the lamentable fall of King <hi>Ioaſh</hi> vnto Idolatrie, which was by the malice of Sathan effected by his Princes; but before we come to ſpeake of the wordes ſet downe in this Text; it ſhall not bee amiſſe to conſider diuers circumſtances going before, which are verie pertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to this place. In which circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, firſt, we may obſerue the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God in preſeruing this yong king <hi>Ioaſh</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17427:4"/>from the cruell tyrannie of <hi>Athalia,</hi> who after the death of <hi>Ahaziah</hi> his father, cauſed all the kings lynage to be ſlaine: to the ende that ſhe might vſurpe the kingdome, and ſo raigne as Queene ouer Iudah and Ieruſalem: Which thing ſhe brought to paſſe for a time, but the Lord who ouerthroweth the practiſes of the wicked, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it pleaſeth him, deliuered this yong infant out of her bloodie hands, by the good policie of <hi>Iehoſheba</hi> his fathers ſiſter, who did ſteale the child away, that he might not be put to death according to the commandement of that blood thirſtie woman, and cauſed him to be kept ſecretly in the bedchamber of the houſe of the Lord: All which time wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Athalia</hi> raigned ouer the people. But when the appointed time was come, and that <hi>Ioaſh</hi> being of the age of ſeuen years, that Grandcaptaine and holy high prieſt of the Lord <hi>Iehoiada,</hi> brought forth this child with great ſolemnitie, and cauſed him to be crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned king ouer the people: and commaunded the vſurping Queene to be put to death, which thing was performed accordingly by the iuſt iudgement of God; ſhe being troaden vnder the feete of horſes. And <hi>Iehoiada</hi> made a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant betweene him and the people,
<note place="margin">2. Chro. 23.16.</note> and the king, that they ſhould be the Lords people, all which time the land inioyed her peace. And <hi>Iehoiada</hi> was protector to the king from time
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17427:4"/>to time, teaching him the feare of the Lord, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the young king grew to be more forward in the Law of God giuen by <hi>Moſes,</hi> as alſo in repairing of the Temple, then any of the Prieſts or Leuites, which zeale and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes of his, continued all the lifetime of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoiada:</hi> which forwardnes of King <hi>Ioaſh</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and repairing of the Temple, as alſo the bloodie Tragedy of <hi>Athalia,</hi> with the courage and boldnes of <hi>Iehoiada,</hi> I will referre you to the chapter going before, as alſo this, out of which I haue choſen my Text, with the 11. and 12. chapters of the 2. booke of the Kings, where the holy Ghoſt hath moſt largely and amplie ſet downe this hiſtorie vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Now let vs come to the words as they lie in order to be handled, <hi>and after the death of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoiada,</hi> &amp;c. In theſe words I obſerue, fiue ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall circumſtances, the three firſt are contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the 17. verſe, the other two in the 18. verſe. In the firſt there is offered vnto our conſiderations by the holy Ghoſt, the time when theſe princes came to ſeduce <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> and that is ſet down in theſe words, <hi>After the death of Iehoiada came the princes of Iuda,</hi> &amp;c. In the ſecond, we are to conſider the manner of their comming in theſe words: <hi>And they did reuerence vnto the King.</hi> In the third, the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and readie conſent of the King vnto their counſell in theſe words: <hi>And the King hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17427:5"/>vnto them.</hi> In the fourth is ſet downe the matter, wherein the king obeyed them, in theſe words. <hi>And they left the houſe of the Lord God of their fathers, and ſerued groues &amp; Idols:</hi> In the fift and laſt is ſet downe the iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, againſt the king, Princes and people, for their rebellion and diſobedience, in theſe words. <hi>And wrath came vpon Iuda and Ieruſalem, becauſe of this their treſpaſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt which is the time, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Sathan ſtirred vp his inſtruments, to wit, theſe princes of Iuda to alienate and withdraw the heart of this yong king, from the true feare and ſeruice of God, wherin he was trained vp by Gods high Prieſt, it is ſaid to be after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> death of <hi>Iehoiada.</hi> By which practiſe of Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may ſee that to be verified in this king, which <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of in his firſt Epiſtle and laſt chapter, <hi>The Diuell our aduerſarie walketh about like a roaring Lion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeking about whom he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure:</hi> And therefore the Apoſtle willeth vs to watch and be ſober, a verie neceſſarie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition for vs, ſeeing the nature of man is ſo inclinable vnto that which is euill. But if it be demaunded why theſe Princes did not goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to put this matter in practiſe before; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere according to the prouerbe, there was a hatch before the doore, that is, <hi>Iehoiada</hi> was liuing; and therefore they knew, that Gods high Prieſt would not ſuffer ſo vild a thing to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17427:5"/>be attempted, but rather would reſiſt their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe; And therefore they watched their time, when there was a doore opened vnto them, by the death of <hi>Iehoiada.</hi> Thus for the moſt part the enemies of the Goſpell waiteth their ſeaſons, when they may do moſt hurt: v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing alſo the meanes by the which they may beſt preuaile againſt the trueth. The which practiſe of theirs. I meane their forwardneſſe in wickedneſſe, ſhould teach vs to be the more watchfull ouer our ſelues and others, then we are. For if Sathan and his inſtruments, to wit, the aduerſaries of the grace of God, will vſe the benefite of the time, againſt the Trueth; how much more ought we, that are Chriſtians to take heed, that wee ſuffer not ſo precious a thing as time, to be pretermitted, but rather we ſhould ſtirre vp our ſelues, while it is called to day, to make our ſaluation ſure, leaſt wee be ſhut out of the Lordes reſt, and the doore of his mercy bolted vp againſt vs, and we knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be let in, it ſhal be ſaid vnto vs, <hi>Depart from me, ye that worke iniquitie.</hi> Againe,
<note place="margin">Matth. 7.23.</note> let vs conſider when it was that the children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el fel away to groſſe Idolatrie, and worſhipped the golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> calfe, which they conſtrained <hi>Aaron</hi> to make, and we ſhall find it was euen in the abſence of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> hee being vpon Mount Sina with the Lord, to receiue the two Tables of the Teſtimonie: a fit oportunitie for Sathan
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17427:6"/>to bring them to Idolatrie. When was it that the tempter came to our Sauiour Chriſt and willed him to commaund ſtones to be made bread,
<note place="margin">Matth. 4.2.3.</note> euen when our Sauiour had faſted fortie dayes and fortienights, and was at the laſt hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie? When was it that <hi>Dauid</hi> committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie with <hi>Bethſhaba,</hi> not when he followed Gods enemies and his in battaile,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.2.</note> but euen then when he tooke his eaſe at home, in his pallace, and walked vpon the roofe thereof? So long as <hi>Sampſon</hi> fought with the vncircumciſed Philiſtines,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.2.</note> and imployed his time againſt his enemies, he could not be taken of them, but after he gaue himſelfe to idleneſſe, and ſlept in the lappe of <hi>Dalilah</hi> his harlot, hee was taken and made blind by the Philiſtines. King <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 19.</note> after he had left off to build the Temple, hee was ſeduced and brought to Idolatrie by women. When was it that <hi>Simon Peter</hi> deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and forſware his Maſter, not ſo long as he was in his companie,
<note place="margin">Mat. 16. Mark. 14. Luke 22.</note> but after our Sauiour Chriſt was taken by the high Prieſts, and hee bathing and warming himſelfe in the high Prieſts hall, he had ſoone forgot his promiſe vnto Chriſt, and before the cocke crew he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed him thrice? And therefore let vs watch ouer our ſelues, and keepe good watch and ward at all times, and in all places, leaſt we be found of our Arch-enemy vnarmed, and let vs buckle on our armour of proofe, that the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17427:6"/>blowes of Sathan, do not pearce it: for as I haue ſaid before, he watcheth his time when he may beſt take vs, at an aduantage, like a cunning maſter of Fence, who will be ſure to giue a venie, if at any time we lie open vnto him. Theſe examples which we haue ſhewed of the fal of good men, may be looking glaſſes for vs all, wherein we may ſee what fleſh and blood is, without Gods ſpirit aſſiſting vs. For who is more holier then was <hi>Dauid,</hi> of whom the Lord ſaid, he was a man after his own hart: or who more ſtronger then <hi>Sampſon,</hi> or who more wiſer then <hi>Salomon:</hi> or who loued Chriſt more then <hi>Peter:</hi> and yet all theſe ſlipped and troad awrie? So that there is not any man that can aſſure himſelfe of ſtanding no, not the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father the Pope himſelfe. And therefore truely is it ſaid, from hence commeth all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, <hi>euen when men ſlept,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13.25.</note> 
               <hi>the enemie came and ſowed tares among the wheate, and went his way:</hi> when men runne not forward in the race of their ſaluation, the diuell laboureth to worke their deſtruction, as afterward it may appeare, by the fall of this King, which by Gods iuſt iudgement was ſlaine by his owne ſeruants, and the Princes deſtroyed, and the people deliuered vp into the handes of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramites, and ſo the land was depriued of their gouernours, and peaceable gouernement.</p>
            <p>Thus beloued we ſhal heare, that the taking
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17427:7"/>away of gouernours, and the want of godly gouernement, is one of the greateſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that the Lord vſeth to inflict vpon the land,
<note place="margin">Eſay. 3.4.</note> as it appeareth in <hi>Eſay,</hi> where the Lorde threatneth, that for the ſinne of the people, he will appoint children to be their Princes, and babes to raigne ouer them, and the people ſhal be oppreſſed one of another, which puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Lord in his mercy hath kept from vs, vntill this day.</p>
            <p>For the which wee haue iuſt cauſe to giue laude and praiſe vnto God, who hath ſo myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly defended our gratious Queene, from the hands of all her enemies, in deſpight of their beards, whom the Lord ſtill continue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, that ſhe may be an old nourſing mother in Iſrael, for his Chriſt his ſake. God (we muſt needs confeſſe) hath taken away ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good <hi>Iehoiadaes</hi> out of this land, I meane godly and ſage Counſellours, which no doubt, is an argument of his diſpleaſure againſt vs for ſinne, and yet what people or nation vnder the heauens, haue enioyed that peaceable and chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian gouernement ſo long time, as wee haue done, and at this preſent do enioy, by the meanes of our bleſſed <hi>Debora.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we haue ſeene what hath fallen out in their times, which may be ſufficient motiues vnto vs, not to detract the time any longer, but as we are forward, in the obſeruation of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17427:7"/>times and ſeaſons, in our outward trauaile and labours; ſo let vs make benefite of this precious time of the Goſpell, that thereby wee may be made fitte for Gods kingdome, when we ſhall be called hence. Thus I will conclude this cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance in a worde, obſeruing this, that as the Angels of God could do nothing in puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of Sodom,
<note place="margin">Gen. 19.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> vntill <hi>Lot</hi> was gone out vnto little Zoar: no more could theſe Princes ſeduce <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> vntill <hi>Iehoiada</hi> was gone to God, after which time, they preuailed with the King, and brought him to Idolatrie: as wee ſhall after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heare. And thus much for the firſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, concerning the time, wherein theſe Princes are ſaid to come vnto the King.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the ſecond, which is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their comming, <hi>and they did reuerence vnto the King:</hi> which is a certaine outward obedience, which they ſhewed, vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of ſubmiſſion, which humilitie and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of theirs, was vſed partly, after an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall manner, to ſteale away the heart of the King vnto Idolatrie: which hath bin a perilous practiſe in all ages, and therefore the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Coloſſians admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth them to take heed of thoſe falſe brethren,
<note place="margin">Col. cap. 2.4.</note> who vnder the colour and pretence of humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, labour to eſtrange and drawe them backe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt. But I wil giue you the words, as they are ſet downe in the Epiſtle, which are theſe.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17427:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>And this I ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>leaſt any man ſhould beguile you, with inticing words: and agayne, Let no man at his pleaſure, beare rule ouer you, by hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of mind.</hi> If you reade the whole Chapter, you may ſee, how carefull the Apoſtle is, leaſt they ſhould be corrupted by falſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and ſo depriued of their Crowne, by the ſubtiltie and counterfeit humilitie of ſome, who laboured to draw them to the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Angels, or to tie them to ceremonies and types in the Law, which were abrogated and ended in Chriſt, and were but ſhadowes of things to come. If the Apoſtle had this care, that hee would not haue them to receiue any thing, ſeeme it neuer ſo little contrary to the Analogie of faith, in the profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Goſpel and the true worſhip of God, how much more ought we to haue a ſpecial care, that we fal not away from grace in Chriſt Ieſus. Well, let vs now ſee further, how dangerous theſe flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hypocrites be, in the Church of God, and in the common wealth: ſurely it many times falleth out, that the very conceit and good o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that we take of ſome, doth much blind our eyes, that wee ſeldome or neuer examine their peeuiſh counſell giuen vnto vs, whether it be of God or no: but their ſpeeches they are as authenticall with vs almoſt, as the articles of our faith.
<note place="margin">1. Iohn 4.1.</note> This is not to trie the ſpirites whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be of God or not. Thus was King
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17427:8"/>
               <hi>Darius</hi> circumuented by the flatterie of his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, in making and ſealing a decree againſt his ſubiect <hi>Daniel,</hi> they no doubt perſwading him, that it would be a matter of great policie, for the trying of the obedience of his new ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and that by that meanes he ſhould finde out thoſe that were diſobedient, which would tend greatly to his good; when as indeed, their purpoſe was nothing els, but to deſtroy <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> complaineth of thoſe flatterers which were in his time, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the twelueth Pſalme, ſaying: <hi>They speake deceitfully euery one vnto his neighbour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 12.</note> 
               <hi>flattering with their lippes, and speaking with a double heart:</hi> but in the next verſe he ſaith, <hi>The Lord cut off all flattering lippes, and the tongue that ſpeaketh proud things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 9.</note> Alſo <hi>Ieremie</hi> the Prophet cryeth out againſt theſe deceiuers, <hi>Let euery one take heed of his neighbour, and truſt you not in any brother, for euery brother will vſe deceit, and euery friend will deale deceitfully, and euery one will deceiue his friend, and will not ſpeake the trueth, for they haue taught their tongues to ſpeake lyes, and take great paynes to do wickedly.</hi> By which place of Scripture wee may ſee, how common a thing it is, for men to worke wickedneſſe, and how hard a matter it is for men to deale faithfully one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This was not only the ſinne of the Iewes, which were then the people of God, and whom
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17427:9"/>the Lorde had choſen vnto himſelfe, from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the nations of the earth; but it is now as commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt vs that are Gentiles, who haue taken vpon vs the profeſſion of the Goſpell. Alſo wee reade that our Sauiour Chriſt was betrayed by the flatterie of <hi>Iudas,</hi> for the Euangeliſt ſaith, that he came vnto his Maſter with theſe wordes:
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.49. Mark. 14. Luke 22.</note> 
               <hi>God ſaue thee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and kiſſed him.</hi> We may reade alſo how <hi>Dauid</hi> that holy man was ſeduced by the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie and deceiueable ſpeeches of <hi>Ziba,</hi> who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> his good ſubiect,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.4.</note> and by him hee was moued to giue away the lands of <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> vnto that fawning and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſycophant <hi>Ziba.</hi> And ſurely, if we will take a litle paynes in reading the Scriptures, we ſhall find how theſe flatterers crept into Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Courtes, as into the Court of King <hi>Saul,</hi> who was the firſt King that raigned ouer Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el;
<note place="margin">1. Reg. 12.</note> who had <hi>Doeg</hi> and others ready to accuſe <hi>Dauid</hi> vnto the King. Alſo king <hi>Roboam</hi> had his flatterers, who cauſed him to ſpeake rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto his people: and ſo <hi>Darius</hi> as we haue heard before, had many about him, that ſought the death of <hi>Daniel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 7.10.</note> We reade alſo of <hi>Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> who had <hi>Amaziah</hi> at his elbow to accuſe <hi>Amos</hi> the Prophet.
<note place="margin">Ezra. 4.8.</note> Alſo wee reade in <hi>Ezra</hi> of <hi>Rehum</hi> the Chauncellour and <hi>Shimſhay</hi> the Scribe with the reſt of their companions, who writ vnto <hi>Artahſhaſhte</hi> the king, accuſing the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17427:9"/>inhabitants of Iudea &amp; Ieruſalem of rebellion, againſt the King and Princes of the land. But what ſhould we ſpeake of more examples out of the Scripture, when we haue daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that teacheth vs, that there is nothing more common at this day then flatterie and deceipt, which men carry vnder the cloake of humilitie, and vſe it as the chiefeſt weapon to fight againſt the children of God. The olde prouerbe being verified in them, that vnder green leanes lieth hidden the viperous Serpent, of whom if we take not heed, and be very wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie we may be ſtung vnto death. So if we take not heed of theſe flattering Sycophants, which are the diuels inſtruments, we may be brought to confuſion of bodie &amp; ſoule, which many times commeth to paſſe by their ſmooth perſwaſions and ſweet in chantments. And yet they are ſuch as beare the world in hand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they are friends to religion, when as their purpoſe is no thing elſe but the ouerthrow of the ſame. Theſe men they ſhroud themſelues in the very boſome of the Church, ſo that they may well be compared to theſe falſe brethren which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the Galathians, after that they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Goſpell from the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> which falſe teachers corrupted the pure doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the holy Ghoſt, and ioyned with it, the obſeruing of diuers ceremonies,
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.</note> which they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17427:10"/>taught as neceſſarie to ſaluation. Wherefore the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſeemeth to wonder at their ſodaine chaunge, and therefore in his Epiſtle to them, after his ſalutation he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth them after this manner. I meruaile, ſaith he, that you are ſo ſoone remoued away vnto another Goſpel from him that hath called you in the grace of Chriſt, which is not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Goſpell, ſaue that there be ſome that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you, and intend to peruert the Goſpell of Chriſt. Therfore if we or an Angel from heauen preach vnto you otherwiſe then that which we haue preached vnto you, let him be accurſed.</p>
            <p>Thus we haue heard what flatterers haue been in the Church of God from time to time, labouring to ſeduce and draw Gods children from true religion and his ſeruice: which may be a ſufficient warning vnto vs as we haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed before, leſt we be carried away vnto falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and become irreligious and profane, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing the doctrine of diuels, for the doctrine of Chriſt. Which many times falleth out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs for want of due care had ouer our ſelues: and therefore it will not be amiſſe for vs, to auoid, as much as may be, the company of the wicked, leaſt by our ſocietie with them, we be drawne to ioyne with them in their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt religion, as alſo in a profane conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Let vs take heed that we lend not our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17427:10"/>eares to the inchanted melodie of thoſe Sytens, whoſe ſongs may breed a ſweet delight in vs, and yet our deſtruction may be at hand. Thus we will conclude this ſecond point, that as <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon</hi> by the courteous carriage of himſelfe ſtale away the hearts of his fathers ſubiects, ſo theſe Princes by their reuerent behauiour, ſtole away the heart of this king from his God. And ſo much for the ſecond circumſtance.</p>
            <p>Now foloweth the three circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance in theſe words, <hi>And the King harkened vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Which is as much as if the holy Ghoſt had ſaid, he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of their counſell, and being deluded by them, he declined from the true ſeruice of God, wherein he had been trained vp all his life time by <hi>Iehoiada</hi> the high Prieſt, and was now fallen away. We muſt not thinke that it was vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the King to heare them, for in that he heard their counſel he ſinned not, but in that he obeyed them, and was contented to be led by them vnto Idolatrie, thereby he incurred the wrath of God, and brought a heauie iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon himſelfe and his ſubiects: And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is the part of all good chriſtians and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſubiects to pray vnto God, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, that it would pleaſe his Maieſtie ſo to inlighten all chriſtian kings and princes of the earth, with the ſpirit of wiſedome and diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that they may auoid and ſlie the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17427:11"/>allurements of the wicked, whom the Lord ſometime ſuffereth to ſit in the place of Magiſtracie, enen to be a rod for the people. For <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>I haue ſeen ſeruants on horſes, &amp; Princes walk as ſeruats on the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> which ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Salomon</hi> may be thus vnderſtood,
<note place="margin">Prou. 10.7.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time both in the Church and Commonwealth, the vnworthie and vnfit ones are preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the worthie: and being ſet at the ſterne of the ſhip, they like vnskilfull Pylots, ſuffer the ſhip to go to wracke. But in this thing we muſt not thinke the hand of God to be wanting, but that hee by his prouidence, vſeth them as a ſcourge to correct his people, as he vſed <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bucadnezer</hi> and <hi>Senacherib</hi> and diuers others, to afflict and perſecute the ſtubborne and diſobedient Iewes: and therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> his counſell is to be liſtned vnto, whereas he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth all kings and rulers of the earth to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelues vnder the hand of God, in theſe words. <hi>Be wiſe now therefore ye Kings, be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned yee Iudges of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſerue the Lord in feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore if there be any that wil learne true wiſedome, and be truly wiſe, they muſt be Gods ſchollers, they muſt bee contented to he are him, ſpeaking vnto them out of his word. And ſo ſoon as they know, that it is the voice of God, their anſwer muſt be obedience, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17427:11"/>muſt ſay with <hi>Samuel, ſpeake on Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant heareth.</hi> Thus we muſt bend our eares vnto God when he ſpeaketh vnto vs by his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters whom he hath placed ouer vs, for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. When the people of Iſrael were to inioy that good land which the Lord had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them by the right of inheritance, and had deſtroyed many nations &amp; kings for their ſakes, what did the Lord require of them in lieu of his wonderous workes. which he wrought vpon <hi>Pharao</hi> &amp; the Aegyptians, &amp; <hi>Sheon</hi> king of the Amorits which dwelt at Heſhbon, and <hi>Og</hi> the king of Baſan, and tooke their Cities, and diuided them among the tribes of Iſrael as we may read in <hi>Deut.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 3.</note> Truly hee requireth this, that they would harken vnto his lawes, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and ſtatutes which he gaue them by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſeruant whom he had placed ouer them in authoritie, as appeareth further in the next chapter of this booke, where hee thus ſpeaketh vnto the people from the Lord. <hi>Now therefore hearken, O Iſrael, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ordinances,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and to the lawes which I teach you, to doe them, that ye may liue and go in and poſſeſſe that land which the Lord God of your fathers giueth you:</hi> And again he ſaith, <hi>Keepe them therfore and do them, for that is your wiſedome and your vnderstanding in the ſight of the people, which ſhall heare of all theſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17427:12"/>ordinances, and ſhall ſay onely this people is wiſe, and of vnderstanding, and a great nation, &amp;c.</hi> Thus euerie one from the higheſt to the loweſt, muſt hearken to the lawes of God ſet downe vnto them in his word to do them, for this is true wiſedome, and true vnderſtanding both before God and men. Yea other nations ſhall be conſtrained to acknowledge and confeſſe that this our people &amp; nation is a wiſe people, and of vndeſtanding: yea further the Lord ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth moſt ſweet promiſes vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they wil hearken vnto his lawes to do them,
<note place="margin">Deut. 28.</note> as we may read in the ſame booke, where alſo he doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce &amp; threaten to lay his curſes vpon them which do the contrarie. And againe in the fifth of this booke, when <hi>Moſes</hi> was to deliuer the law written in Tables of ſtone, which he had receiued of the Lord to deliuer vnto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he called all the people together, and ſaid vnto them.
<note place="margin">Deut. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Heare, O Iſrael, the ordinances and lawes which I propoſe to you this day.</hi> And againe in the next chapter he hath the like words ſaying. <hi>Heare therfore, O Iſrael, and take heed to do it.</hi> And again he ſaith,
<note place="margin">Deut. 6.</note> 
               <hi>heare O Iſrael, the Lordour God is Lord onely.</hi> And thus as <hi>Moſes</hi> laboured y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the people of Iſrael ſhould apply their eares &amp; hearts to heare and to do that which he taught them from the Lord: euen ſo ſhould we apply the ſame, and lay them vp in our hearts with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17427:12"/>bleſſed <hi>Marie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and ponder them to our fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comfort. But it is the nature of man, to haue his eares open, to heare the counſell of men many times before the counſel of God, and according to the affection we beare vnto them, we are conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to ſuffer our ſelues to be led by them, whether it be with or againſt the truth: whereby many times it falleth out to our ouerthrow &amp; deſtruction as we ſhal here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after heare.</p>
            <p>Now let vs conſider the manifold dangers, which we make our ſelues ſubiect vnto, by len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our eares to the counſell of wicked men. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Can a man carrie fire in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, &amp; not be burnt?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 6.27.</note> No more can we imbrace wicked counſell, but we bring dammage vnto our ſelues. As appeareth by the example of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> the king of Iſrael, who refuſed the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the graue and wiſe ancients, who willed him to ſpeake kindly, and deale louingly with thoſe that came vnto him; but not regarding their counſel, he took the aduice of wicked and deſperate youths, who aduiſed him to ſpeake roughly or churliſhly vnto them, ſaying, <hi>My least part ſhal be heauier then my fathers loynes: if my father did chaſtice you with rods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 12.</note> 
               <hi>I wil cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you with ſcourges or ſcorpions.</hi> But what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed? a lamentable ſequell; The kingdome of <hi>Dauid</hi> was rent a ſunder, and the Tribes of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17427:13"/>diuided. Alſo we read of the young Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, being perſwaded to eate bread by the old Prophet, where the Lord had commanded the contrarie, and by that meanes he procured to himſelfe a fearefull death,
<note place="margin">1. King. 13.</note> being ſlaine with a Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So <hi>Michaiah</hi> was perſwaded by the kings Chamberlaine to ſpeak vnto the king like vnto all the reſt of the Prophets, who ſaid vnto him by theſe words, <hi>let thy words be like vnto theirs:</hi> and ſurely he had many reaſons to moue him thereunto, among the which, this might be one ſpeciall reaſon,
<note place="margin">1. King. 22.</note> that there was 400. Prophets that conſented and ioyned together, to ſpeake good vnto the king. 2. Another reaſon was this, that he was aduiſed by a great courtier, and a man of account, but this aboue all, might be a ſufficient motiue to induce him, that to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the counſel of ſo many prophets might coſt him his life.
<note place="margin">Exod. 13.2.</note> But <hi>Michah</hi> had learned this leſion, that he muſt not follow a multitude to do euill, and therefore hee returned this anſwere, <hi>as the Lord liueth, what the Lord ſpeaketh vnto me, that will I ſpeake:</hi> And therfore we are not to follow high nor low, young nor old, friend nor kinſman, any further, then is agreeable to the word of our eternall God. Nay we are not to follow the godly any further then they follow Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.17.</note> For <hi>Paul</hi> biddeth vs to follow him, as he was a follower of Chriſt. Then much
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17427:13"/>leſſe may we follow the counſel of wicked and prophane men. Further let vs heare what y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Lord ſaith by <hi>Moſes</hi> vnto <hi>Iſrael: If thy brother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 13.</note> 
               <hi>the ſonne of thy mother, or thine owne ſonne, or thy daughter, or thy wife that lieth in thy boſome, or thy friend that is vnto thee as thine own ſoule, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thee ſecretly,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Let vs go and ſerue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods &amp;c. thou ſhalt not conſent vnto him, nor heare him, neyther ſhall thine eye pitie him, thy hand ſhall be first vpon him,</hi> meaning to ſee him puniſhed: So that we ſee, that wicked counſell, ſpecially in the ſeruice and worſhip of God, muſt not go ſcot-free or vnpuniſhed: how much leſſe are we to ſuffer our ſelues, to be ledde as captiues by them, howſoeuer they ſeeme to affect vs: for it is the policie of Sathan many times, to vſe thoſe that are neere vnto vs to alienate and draw our hearts from God, and that wee ſhould not perfourme thoſe things which the Lord hath commanded vs, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the practiſe of Sathan, who vſed <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> the Apoſtle to ſtay our Sauiour Chriſt from Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the Euangeliſt recordeth, that when our Sauiour bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to tel his Diſciples of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and of his ſuffering there: <hi>Peter</hi> tooke him aſide, and began to rebuke him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Maſter, pitie thy ſelfe, this ſhall not be vnto thee,</hi> then our Sauiour looked back &amp; ſaid vnto him, <hi>Get thee behind me Sathan, thou art an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17427:14"/>vnto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.12.23.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe thou vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt not the things that are of God, but the things that are of men.</hi> Againe, we may reade in <hi>Amos</hi> of politike <hi>Amazia,</hi> who gaue counſell vnto the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> to flee into the land of Iuda, and there to eate his bread, and to prophecie, vſing theſe words as a reaſon to perſwade him, that it was the Kings chappell and the Kings court: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazia</hi> fearing that his prophecying there, might be a meanes to turne the King, but the Prophet was ſo farre from hearkening vnto him, that hee thundred Gods iudgements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him,
<note place="margin">Amos 7.12.13.</note> ſaying: <hi>Thus ſayth the Lorde, thy wife ſhall be a harlot in the citie, and thy ſonnes and thy daughters ſhall fall by the ſword, and thy land ſhall be diuided by lyne, and thou ſhalt die in a polluted land, and Iſrael ſhall ſurely go into captiuitie forth out this land.</hi> Thus if wee will be Chriſts ſouldiers, and ſtand for him and the glory of our God, let vs ſet our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sathan and his inſtruments, putting vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs our ſpirituall armour, and not fearing them, but as Chriſt commanded vs to learne of him humilitie,
<note place="margin">Matth. 11.</note> ſo let vs alſo learne of him courage and boldneſſe, to reſiſt and reprehend (as hee did <hi>Peter</hi>) their wicked counſell, who ſpeake vnto vs from Sathan, that ſent them, or els their counſel is carnal;
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> but as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, that <hi>fleſhly luſts fight againſt the ſoule:</hi> ſo fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17427:14"/>counſel fights againſt the ſoule: and as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, <hi>An angrie countenance driueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a ſlaundering tongue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 25.</note> ſo an angrie rebuke and a ſharpe reprehenſion driueth away a worldly, fleſhly and diuelliſh counſellour. What gayned <hi>Ahab</hi> by following the counſell of <hi>Ieſabel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg 22.</note> in taking away the vineyard of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both?</hi> ſurely his reward was death, the Lorde meeteth with his wickedneſſe, that he, being in his chariot, notwithſtanding his armour, hee was ſlaine with an arrow, which pearced the ioyntes of his brigandyne: the like iudgement the Lord inflicted vpon <hi>Iehoram</hi> his ſonne by <hi>Iehu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 17.</note> whom the Lord vſed further in the puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of <hi>Ieſabel Ahabs</hi> counſellour, whom he commanded to be caſt out of the window, and the bellies of hungrie dogs became the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre of her corps.</p>
            <p>And as the Lord recorded the wickedneſſe of <hi>Amelech</hi> for oppoſing himſelfe againſt Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,
<note place="margin">Exod. 27.</note> ſo the Lord hath recorded the wickedneſſe of <hi>Ahab, Ioram</hi> and <hi>Ieſabel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 21.</note> and ſent his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to foretell the iudgements that ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue. What ſucceſſe had <hi>Abſolon</hi> in following the counſell of <hi>Achitophel?</hi> notwithſtanding the ſcripture reporteth of him to be a man of ſingular beautie and louelineſſe, and yet the earth refuſed any longer to beare him, and the heauens would not receiue him, and therefore
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17427:15"/>he hanged betwixt heauen &amp; earth by the haire of the head, whoſe example may be a looking glaſſe for all ſuch monſters,
<note place="margin">1. Reg. 18.</note> who are ſo in loue with their locks, that they beſtow more time in trimming of them, then in any exerciſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion:
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 17.</note> and <hi>Achitophel</hi> his counſeller hanged himſelfe; a iuſt reward for rebels and traytors. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> foreſeeing the manifold dangers, and miſchiefes that men fall into by walking in the counſell of wicked men, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thus.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is that man that walketh not in the counſell of the vngodly:</hi> which bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the Lord graunt vnto all them that feare him.</p>
            <p>Now as we haue heard how dangerous out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enemies are vnto vs, and how they labour by all wayes and meanes to ouerthrow religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both generally and particularly, ſo we muſt alſo be very watchfull, ouer our home-bred e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, which is our owne concupiſcence, and the vntowardnes of our corrupt nature, which maketh continuall warre againſt the ſpirit: and therefore it is very neceſſary, that wee ſhould labour to expell thoſe traytors out of vs, or els it will little boote vs to fight againſt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies abroad.
<note place="margin">Gregorie in moral.</note> And therefore one ſaith, it is in vaine to fight againſt the enemie in the field, if we harbour a traytor within the wals. There is no worſe counſeller, then that which we ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17427:15"/>about with vs, which are as dangerous vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, as the counſellours of <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> which is our corrupt affections, which is well called of one, a domeſticall traytor, and a ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious counſeller, for that it walketh, ſtandeth, ſitteth, ſleepeth and dwelleth with vs. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle S.
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> willeth the Galathians to <hi>walke in the ſpirite, and then you ſhall not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>fulfill the luſtes of the fleſh, for the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh.</hi> But the holy Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines doth moſt notablie handle at large this combate betweene the ſpirite and the fleſh,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> where the Apoſtle bringeth in his owne deeds, to be contrary to the will of the ſpirit. Now if this bleſſed Apoſtle and elect ſeruant of God, who was regenerate by the power of the ſpirite, did find in himſelfe this imbecillitie and weakeneſſe, how much more may we behold in our ſelues our groſſe impieties and manifold rebellions againſt our mercifull father, and ſweete Sauiour Chriſt, whoſe ſides and heart we newly pearce, crucifying againe the Lord of life. Let vs therefore not onely croppe the branches of ſinne, as to abſtaine from the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew of euill, but let vs labour rather to plucke vp ſinne by the rootes in our ſelues, ſo that we may wholy giue ouer our ſelues not as ſeruants to ſinne, but as ſeruants to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17427:16"/>praying vnto God continually for the aſſiſtance of his holy ſpirite, ſo that all our thoughtes, words, works and wayes, may be ordered by the rule and ſquare of his bleſſed and reuealed word: and let vs bring our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the touchſtone which is the word of God,
<note place="margin">Iob. 31.</note> that we may trie them as gold is tryed in the furnace: and let vs be like vnto <hi>Iob,</hi> that as he made a couenant with his eyes, ſo let vs make a couenant with our heartes, that wee ſuffer them not to ſtray from the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord. For our heart is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine from whence ſpringeth all our actions, whether they be good or euill. And this is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall diſeaſe among vs at this day, the worſer ſort are not onely infected with it, but many of the better ſort can be content to beare a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall good liking towards the word of God and his commandements, but ſeldome or neuer do they labor to approue their hearts before God, in the performance of their ſeuerall duties, which they owe vnto God or vnto their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; but they rather content themſelues, with the very name or title of Profeſſors of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, when as in the meane time, they ought to haue conſidered, that the very neglect of any one dutie, commanded vs in the worde, and knowne vnto vs, redoundeth to the contempt of the Lorde himſelfe, who is the Law-giuer,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17427:16"/>and therefore the right peruſing of the ſeueral duties commanded vs in his Law, will bring vs from our pretended profeſſion, to an approued practiſe of ſuch duties as are commanded vs of the Lord: for the Lord beholdeth not the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward obedience alone, but he looketh to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the heart,
<note place="margin">Pro. 23.26. Deut 6.</note> and therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith in the perſon of God, <hi>My ſonne, giue me thy heart:</hi> and the Lord in Deut. commandeth the children of Iſrael, to loue him with all their heart, with all their ſoule, and all their ſtrength. Thus we haue heard how king <hi>loaſh</hi> hearkened with conſent vnto the counſell of his Princes: alſo, how the Lord hath puniſhed many other, for following of wicked counſell: and againe, how the godly haue refuſed to be led by it: and againe, how wee are to ſet our ſelues againſt home-bred counſellers, namely our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence and fleſhly affections, which like traytors and rebels haue conſpired our ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw: and laſtly, how we are to approue our hearts before God in the practiſe of thoſe ſeuerall duties, which he hath commaunded vs in his word: and ſo much for the third circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, where it is ſaid, that <hi>he hearkened vnto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it followeth to be conſidered, wherein the King is ſaid to haue followed their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, in theſe words. <hi>They left the houſe of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17427:17"/>Lord God of their fathers, and ſerued groues and idols.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which words it appeareth, that as they left off to ſerue God, according as they had bin inſtructed and taught by <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ehotad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in the lawes and commandements giuen by <hi>Moſes;</hi> ſo alſo they left the place of Gods worſhip, namely the houſe of God, and the holy temple built by <hi>Salomon,</hi> and ſerued their Idols in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their own inuention. But firſt let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how God is ſaid to be <hi>the God of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> God calleth himſelfe. <hi>The God of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, the God of Iſaac and the God of Iacob,</hi> and bound himſelfe by a conenant to be a God vnto them and to their ſeed for euer: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iacob</hi> when he ſtood in ſeare of his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> turneth himſelfe by prayer vnto God; ſaying,
<note place="margin">Gen. 32.</note> 
               <hi>O God of my father Abraham, and God of my father Iſaac &amp;c.</hi> As the Lorde would haue no other gods ioyned with him, ſo he gaue commandement for the maner of his worſhip, how it ſhould be performed, and alſo for the place, where the Iewes ſhould aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble themſelues to offer their ſacrifices, and other rites and ceremonies, commanded them in the Law by <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 12.5.</note> as appeareth in Deut. where <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh thus vnto them, <hi>You ſhall ſeeke the place which the Lord your God ſhal chuſe out of all your tribes to put his name
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17427:17"/>there to dwell, and thither thou ſhalt come.</hi> And againe he ſaith,
<note place="margin">Deut. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Take heede that thou offer not thy burnt offerings in euery place that thou ſeeſt, but in the place which the Lord ſhal chuſe in one of your tribes.</hi> And therefore the Arke which was made did repreſent Gods preſence, and was placed in Shilo, where ſome thinke it remayned more then three hundred yeeres, and afterwards was remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into other places, till the appointed time that God commanded <hi>Salomon</hi> to build the Temple: after which time the Iſraelites were commaunded to reſort thither, for the performance of ſuch ſacrifices and other rites and ceremonies, which were required of them by the Lord: all which ſeruice and worſhip continued till the comming of Chriſt: although it were altogether corrupted amongſt the Iewes, as alſo amongſt the high Prieſts with the Scribes and Phariſees, and after that <hi>Salomon</hi> had builded the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, hee made his prayer vnto God, that the Lord would haue his eares open vnto the prayers of his ſeruants, which ſhould pray vnto him in that place, and that if any ſhould be ledde into captiuitie, and returne vnto the Lorde by repentance,
<note place="margin">2. Chro. 6 1. King. 7.</note> with their faces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Temple, that hee would be ready to heare them: the Lord anſwering his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17427:18"/>in the next Chapter: Thus they left off to ſerue God, and became Idolaters, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted Gods iudgements againſt themſelues. What ſhould I ſpeake of our Italian and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh worſhippers, when as euery man that hath any ſight at all, may ſee their groſſe and palpable dealing, in abſenting themſelues from our aſſemblies, and ſaigning vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a religion of their own braine. So that as they haue forſaken the fellowſhip of Gods children in the congregation, ſo haue they forſaken God himſelfe, and ſet vp Idols in God his ſtead, caſting downe themſelues before them, and worſhipping them: but if they will ſay they worſhip not the Idoll or image, but God in them or by them, this is groſſe idolatrie, befofore God. But bleſſed be God for that it hath pleaſed his Maieſty to ſtir vp our gracious Queene to tread in the ſteps of good <hi>Ezechtas</hi> and <hi>Ioſias</hi> to deſtroy the Idoll groues and temples with thoſe high places, or rather high Altars which were ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for the ſacrifices of their Maſſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their ſuperſtition. Another ſort there are that haue left our publike aſſemblies,
<note place="margin">Browniſts.</note> ſaying, we haue neither Church nor lawfull miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and yet haue ſome of them confeſſed that the knowledge which they haue, they firſt came vnto it by the hearing of the word of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17427:18"/>God in our congregations, preached by thoſe whom now they do condemne: they pretend purity in the profeſſion of the Goſpel, and ſee not that their proceeding cannot be warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the word, nay ſome of them haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that ſince that they left of to heare the word preached, they haue found themſelues very colde in religion. Theſe with others are puffed vp with a certaine proud conceit of themſelues, and doe beare themſelues very ſtubbornly towards their ſuperiours, eyther forgetting, or elſe not hauing learned the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of meeknes and humility of our Sauiour Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.</note> I will not ſpeake of the idle life of ſome of them, how they haue neglected their calling, wandring from place to place, and liuing by the labours of others, but it were well if we could approue our humility in ſome meaſure before God and men, with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Dauid,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>My beart is not haughty, neither are my eyes lofty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 13.</note> 
               <hi>neither haue I walked in great matters and hid from me:</hi> by which words the Prophet approoueth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe before God as one of his, and purgeth himfelſe from this ſin of pride. There are alſo ſome which although they leaue not of alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to heare the word, yet how much time do they ſpend in reading bookes vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and prophane, which tendeth much
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17427:19"/>to the hurt of a good mind, being ſtuffed with many lies and tales, as the booke of King <hi>Arthur,</hi> Sir <hi>Tristram,</hi> Sir <hi>Lancclet,</hi> the booke of <hi>Skogging, Beuis</hi> of Southhamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, the hundreth vnſauory tales filled with ribaldry, I ſay nothing of amorous bookes, yea, rather venemous bookes flowing with laſciuiouſnes and vncleannes, and ſuch other dregs of the like ſtamp, which were ſitter for the fire then the preſſe, &amp; in theſe toyes while many do ſpend their time in reading of them they neuer complaine of wearines, although they ſpend diuers houres in the forenoone, and alſo in the afternoone: but the hearing of the word of God is irkſome vnto them, &amp; yet they can be content to driue away the time (as they ſay) which I haue ſhewed before, ſhould be better imployed: yea the long win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nights muſt by that meanes be ſhortned; and as the eares of many are very attentiue, ſo their hearts are carried away with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain delight of ſuch ſtuffe as they heare out of ſuch prophane bookes, but as for the ſacred book of God the holy Bible, it lieth in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner being ſeldome vſed (if there be any). And theſe although they do not altogether refuſe to heare the word of God, yet it hath not wrought ſuch a reliſh in them,
<note place="margin">Act. 17.11</note> that with the noblemen of <hi>Berea</hi> they ſearch the ſcripture
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17427:19"/>and therefore as the Lord ſaith, <hi>Why takeſt thou my wordin thy mouth, and hateſt to be reformed?</hi> So it may be ſaid to thoſe, <hi>why hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thou my word, and hateſt to be reformed.</hi> Wel, for as much as it is the work of God his ſpirit, both to will and to doe the thing that is good, we muſt haue our recourſe vnto God (by praier) to work thoſe things in vs which nature will not afford, that we hearing the word, may reape ſuch profit as that we may reliſh and taſte it to the building of vs vp in Chriſt. Now as it is the part of all men to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for a ſauing knowledge, ſo alſo muſt this knowledge beget a practiſe in all thoſe that profeſſe the Goſpel, following the example of the godly in the ſcripture, who after they had the tree of ſaith planted in them, they brought forth fruit accordingly, as appeareth by <hi>Zacheus,</hi> Luk. 19.
<note place="margin">Luke. 19</note> and that we may be the better ſtirred vp to vſe the means for faith, let vs conſider the example of ſome whom the holy Ghoſt hath ſet out vnto vs, and our ſauiour Chriſt himſelfe vpbraiding the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne Iewes bringeth in that exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple worthy of memory, to wit, the Queene of the ſouth, who is ſaid to come from the vttermoſt part of the earth, to heare the wiſedome of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> and behold ſaith he, a greater then <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> is here, ſhe is ſaid to haue left for a time
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17427:20"/>her fruitful country Arabia called Saba, when as ſhe might haue had ſufficient excuſes for her ſtay at home;
<note place="margin">Chro. 2. ch. 9 Mat, 12</note> firſt the weaknes of her ſex; with the longues of the iourney, the perill of her owne perſon, inſurrections and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in her abſence, many things of moment might haue ſtayed her; but ſhe laying aſide all excuſes whatſoeuer, came with a reſolute purpoſe to heare the wiſedome of <hi>Salomon.</hi> We haue heard how the noble men of <hi>Berea</hi> ſearched the ſcripture after they had heard the Doctrine of the Apoſtles. Alſo I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that famous Ladie of <hi>Herods</hi> court ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with other godly women, being the wife of <hi>Herods</hi> ſteward, whom the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt reporteth that they went to heare our Sauiour preach out of a ſhip, they ſtanding by the Sea ſide,
<note place="margin">Luke. 8</note> there being a throng of many people, it ſhould ſeeme ſhee ſtood not vpon her diſparagement, or diſcredit which ſhee might reape by her going to the Sermon of Chriſt, and that alſo to the ſea ſide: neither yet did ſhe much reſpect her own caſe, for we do not read of any pewes ſtooles, or cuſhins that were prepared for her: No, no ſhee ſtood not vpon any of theſe things as many of our tender dames doe now a daies, who may if they will heare the word of God in our publique aſſemblies in the Church, and not
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17427:20"/>trauell as they did farre for it, but this muſt be the worke of the ſpitit of God in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as no doubt it was in this Ladie, and the other wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who went with an earneſt deſire to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit themſelues by the doctrine of Chriſt, which deſire if it be wanting, in any that vſeth to heare the word, they ſhall hardly profit by it. And therefore as it is ſaid, that <hi>Simeon</hi> came into the Temple by the motion of the fpirit and found Chriſt, ſo if we will finde Chriſt to our ſaluation,
<note place="margin">Luke. 2</note> let vs craue at the hands of God the aſſiſtance of his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, when we frequent the exerciſes of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thus much for the fourth point. Now it followeth in the laſt circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance, <hi>And wrath came vpon Iuda &amp; Ieruſalem, becauſe of their treſpaſſe.</hi> The wrath of God as one ſaith, is not an heat of a troubled mind, as it is in vs poore wretches; but a iuſt reuenge and puniſhment of our ſinnes, and the ſcripture doth very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably ſpeake vnto vs according to our capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie in attributing vnto God, wrath, furie, and indignation, and it is, becauſe that we for the moſt part are ſo blockiſh, as that we cannot apprehend as we ought, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his diuine Maieſtie, neither yet ſeare his iudgements; the wrath of God is ſo feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a thing that no conſuming fire, or the moſt terrible things that are vſed of the Lord
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17427:21"/>to correct his people, cannot at the ful ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently informe vs of the great vehemencie thereof, the Prophet ſaith, <hi>If a man will not turne, he will whet his ſword, he hath bent his bow and made it readie, he hath prepared the instruments of death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>he hath prepared his arrowes againſt the perſecutors,</hi> &amp;c. The Lord will not ſuffer the wicked to goe ſcotfree and vnpuniſhed, for ſo it ſtandeth with his iuſtice, and yet he is ſlow to anger, and ſuch a one as is ſorie for our offences. We haue many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camples in the ſcripture how hee meeteth with all ſorts of ſinners, yea the Lord ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not our grand parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> but for their offences, he baniſhed then out of Eden, which was a moſt fruitfull and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull place, and alſo inflicted a grieuous puniſhment vpon them firſt, ſaying to the woman, <hi>I will greatly increaſe thy ſorrowes, and thy conceptions. In ſorrow ſhalt thou bring forth thy children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and thy deſire ſhalbe ſubiect to thy husband, and he ſhall rule ouer thee.</hi> Alſo vnto <hi>Adam</hi> he ſaid: <hi>Becauſe thou haſt obeyed the voyce of thy wife, and haſt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the tree whereof I commaunded thee, ſaying thou ſhalt not eate of it: curſed is the earth for thy ſake, &amp;c.</hi> And further he ſaith, <hi>In the ſweat of thy face thou ſhalt eate bread till thou returne to the earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 7.</note> For ſinne the old
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17427:21"/>worlde was deſtroyed with the flood.
<note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> 
               <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> was conſumed with fire and brimſtone. <hi>Corah</hi> and his company went downe into the bowels of the earth. The Iſraelites were grieuouſly puniſhed many times for their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience and manifold rebellions, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the books of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. <hi>Dauid</hi> loſt threeſcore and ton thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men,
<note place="margin">Chro. 1. chap. 21.</note> whom the Lorde deſtroyed with the peſtilence. <hi>Saul</hi> was depoſed from his kingdome, afflicted and vexed with a diuell, and after ſlaine, as alſo his owne ſonnes, his armour bearer and his men in one day. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Salomon</hi> of 12. tribes loſt ten. <hi>Sedecias</hi> was ledde captiue into Babilon,
<note place="margin">2. King. 4. Exod. 14.27.</note> and his eyes put out. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> with his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots ouerwhelmed in the red Sea. <hi>Herod</hi> came to a horrible end. <hi>Senacharib</hi> ſlaine by his owne ſeruants. Chron. 2. chap. 32. <hi>Ieſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell</hi> caſt out of the window. <hi>Ionas</hi> caſt into the ſea. Ionas 1. A certaine Prophet ſlaine by a lyon. 1. Kin. 20. The children that moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the man of God <hi>Elizeus,</hi> were torne with Beares. Infinite are the examples of Gods wrath and heauie diſpleaſure vpon the wicked and prophane as wee may reade of <hi>Eſau, Abſolon, Achitophel, Iudas,</hi> with many other. Yea the Lorde hath puniſhed many Kingdoms for ſinne: the Romaines, the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17427:22"/>of the Chaldeans, the kingdome of the Perſians, the kingdom of the Macedonians, the Carthaginians: nay, the Lord hath not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the famous citie of Ieruſalem with the holy temple where his Namedwelt. But as he did often afflict the Iewes his choſen peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſo at the laſt he made Ieruſalem eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ground, neuer to be reedified againe: which was eſpecially for the contempt of his word which hee ſent vnto them by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and alſo for reiecting of our Sauiour Chriſt with his doctrine, and myracles which he wrought among them, and therefore our Sauiour prophecyeth of their perpetuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. <hi>Paul</hi> preached to the Coloſſians, Hierapolitans and Laodiceans, but they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned his doctrine, and therefore one wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth,
<note place="margin">Oriofius lib. 7. cap. 5.</note> that the earth opened and ſwallowed them vp, But what ſhould I ſay, <hi>the reward of ſinne is death:</hi> and <hi>the ſoule that ſinneth ſhal die:</hi> and to draw to an end, this puniſhment which the Lord laid vpon <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> the Princes, and people, may be ſufficient to admoniſh vs to beware of Idolatrie or any other ſinne, leaſt we pull the like iudgements vpon our owne heads: and let vs remember what one ſaith; the puniſhment of one is an example for all: then it remaineth, that as we haue heard that God is iuſt in puniſhing of ſinne as well in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17427:22"/>his children as in the wicked, that we labour to preuent his wrath, by turning vnto him, before wee feele the like iudgement: and let vs not paſſe by any affliction or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble which hee vſeth to lay vpon any, or vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelues, but rather to lay them to our hearts, making that vſe of them, for the which they are ſent, which is, that we may by them he made more fitte for God: this vſe made <hi>Dauid</hi> of his troubles, when he ſaid;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. Ecclc. 7.</note> 
               <hi>It was good for me that I was in trouble &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith; <hi>It is better to go to the houſe of mourning, then to the houſe of feaſting; for the liuing will lay it to his heart.</hi> So it is better ſometime to be inaduerſitie, then in proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; for good men will make vſe of it, but it is the policie of Sathan, that wee ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer apply God his iudgements, which we ſee to be vpon others, vnto our ſelues, in ſuch ſort, as wee ſhould thereby profit in repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.
<note place="margin">Sinne vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, what are the effects following it.</note> Amongſt many good meanes to draw men to vnfaigned repentance of their ſinnes before God, and in their owne heart; this, me thinketh, ſhould not be of the leaſt force, wel and deepely to weigh the feareful effects, that finne vnrepented of, bringeth foorth in the ſight of God, and men, and in their owne minds, that liue ſo impenitently.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt it quencheth, yea driueth away
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17427:23"/>the power and working of Gods ſpirit in vs, which being moſt holy and pure of it ſelfe, cannot abide to dwel in, much leſſe to worke effectually in an vncleane ſoule and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, it hindereth vs from the right and holy profit that we might receiue by the worde of God, which is not profitable nor powerfull in any, but thoſe that tremble thereat, as God ſpeaketh in <hi>Eſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, it ſhutteth our mouthes from inuocation, prayer, and calling vpon Gods name, for how can wee call vpon him, in whom we beleeue not, or how can we be ſaid to beleeue, whileſt we continue in our ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Fourthly it cauſeth God to ſtop his eares from hearing our prayers, or graunting our requeſts, for God heareth not ſinners: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the prayers of the wicked are abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, as the Scripture ſaith.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Laſtly, it prouoketh God, (that of his owne nature is moſt inclinable vnto all mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie) through our ſinnes, to let in vpon vs all the floods of his eternall Iuſtice, to our feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full confuſion, our ſinnes and nothing els ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſeparation betwixt vs and God, as the Prophet affirmeth.
<note place="margin">Iſay. 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt many things,
<note place="margin">Sinne to be repreſſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon all eſtates and perſons.</note> that ſhould repreſſe the rage of ſinne before we fall, or els ſhould
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17427:23"/>moue vs to vnfeigned repentance, after ſinne is committed, this, me thinketh, ſhould be one of great force and power, namely, that euen ſome particular mens ſinnes vnrepented of, or wincked at and not puniſhed, may and do iuſtly prouoke Gods heauie indignation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all eſtates and perſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1 As firſt for example againſt the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, becauſe that God hauing put the ſword of holy authoritie into their hands, for the puniſhment of euill, and maintenance of good, they haue not (according to Gods word their duties, and the haynouſneſſe of the offence) puniſhed the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Againſt Miniſters,
<note place="margin">Malac. 22.</note> becauſe God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing put into their mouthes, the worde of trueth, and appointing them thereby to cut downe ſinne, they contrary vnto Gods ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commandement, and their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and calling, haue bin tongue-tied and durſt not ſpeake.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Againſt the people, becauſe that they (keeping themſelues notwithſtanding in the compaſſe of their Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>calling) haue not by ſharpe reproofe, either ſhewed their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes of the ſinnes committed or their loue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring the conuerſion of the offending partie.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And againſt the parties committing it,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17427:24"/>becauſe they through impenitencie and hard heartedneſſe continuing in ſinne, and hauing few or no meanes for their reclaiming, can not but looke for fearefull indignation, and wrath from the Lord for the ſame.</p>
            <p>But the wicked do deferre their repentance not thinking Gods iudgementes to be at hand, when as indeed the Lorde hath ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out his arme already to ſtrike. But it is otherwiſe with the children of God, who are not drawne by a ſlauiſh feare of puniſhment vnto obedience, but rather of a childlike loue they beare vnto God their father, through and by which loue, they perfourme willingly that which the Lord hath commaunded: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that meaſure of grace, which God hath giuen them, omitting alſo the contrary through loue, which obedience is no doubt acceptable to God.</p>
            <p>The Lord for his Chriſts ſake, touch our hearts with ſuch loue to his Maieſtie, that all our wayes may pleaſe him, and that as wee haue inioyed many yeeres of peace and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of temporary bleſſings, with the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of his glorious Goſpell, vnder the raigne of our moſt dread Soueraigne, ſo let vs call vpon his name for the continuance of all his mercies with the preſeruation of our gracious Queene: that although our ſinnes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17427:24"/>haue prouoked the contrary, yet that hee would graunt vs theſe things, for his Chriſt his ſake our onely Lorde and Sauiour, to whom with God the Father and the holy Ghoſt, we acknowledge to be due, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in our hearts to yeeld all praiſe, glory and honor, both now and euermore. Amen.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>What ere thou be, pray God alwayes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To bleſſe our Queene with happie dayes:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whoſe wiſdome vnder God ſo long,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hath kept this Realme from forreine wrong.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
